<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SIMLab</title>
    <description>We help organizations use technology to do better.</description>
    <link>http://simlab.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://simlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Our brown bag lunch and podcast: Mobile money in the last mile</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The discussion is available for download as a podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/simlab-podcast/id1056814879?mt=2&quot;&gt;via iTunes&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/socialimpactlab/only-tough-options-1&quot;&gt; Soundcloud&lt;/a&gt; , and we expect the insights gained will be valuable for the international development and tech community for practitioners and beyond. Releasing the event as a podcast is an experiment in providing resources for the community that live on beyond the work itself—let us know what you think in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mobile-money-in-rural-low-infrastructure-communities&quot;&gt;Mobile money in rural, low infrastructure communities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post_images/sacco.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sacco&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event marked the release publication of our case study titled:&lt;a href=&quot;/files/SIMLab Case Study - Mobile money in the last mile.pdf&quot;&gt;SIMLab’s experience in Kenya: Implementing a mobile money management tool and training approach in the last mile&lt;/a&gt; It covers the first direct technology implementation project ever carried out by SIMLab’s first ever direct project implementation, and it and the project were funded by the Global Poverty Action Fund of the UK Department for International Development. SIMLab ordinarily supports other organizations to use inclusive technology in their work, and usually works with local partners together with other actors from the international community. For this project, we built on our presence in Nairobi to work directly with Kenyan organizations, and had the opportunity therefore to gather learning and data. Needless to say, there were numerous lessons learned throughout the two-year grant, which comes to an end in December 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anticipated outcome of the DFID project is to reduce poverty in low-income areas of Kenya by providing mobile money management tools to organizations and small to medium-sized businesses (SMEs) who had not yet taken up mobile money. At the outset, the grant was inspired by our desire to build better ‘middleware’ to support these types of organizations to begin using mobile money, based on FrontlineSMS, and called ‘Payments.’ During the course of the grant, our relationship to the software shifted slightly as SIMLab spun out FrontlineSMS as a for profit. This allowed our definition of success to broaden from being product-centric to process- and learning-focused, and we were able to support more mobile money platforms including those provided by the operator, Safaricom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DFID GPAF project was extremely valuable to SIMLab as it allowed us to interface directly with the tools we and FrontlineSMS created, and more importantly the tool users (organizations) and the people the tool was meant to affect. The relationship gave us the opportunity to gain a deep insight into the realities and unique contexts of last-mile organizations as we guided them through the process of adopting mobile money. Through this high-touch work, which included organizational development and strategy, communications, and technology training, we observed the barriers encountered by organizations in operationalizing mobile money. We worked with 40 organizations throughout the grant whom we expected to go through similar hurdles, successes and timelines in their journey to becoming cashless. What we found, and reported in our case study, was that the barriers to adoption were far higher than we’d thought, and the requirements of a successful project in terms of support and staff times were similarly large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-panel&quot;&gt;The Panel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our findings, while sobering, were much less controversial for the other panelists than we’d imagined. Overall, we agree that even in a country where 90% of households have access to mobile money, introducing mobile money into businesses and operationalizing it, as Leo Tobias rightly argues, is “terribly complicated.” This narrative is typically overpowered in much of the writing about mobile money, by the one which casts Kenya as a mobile digital economy, the ‘Silicon Savannah’, and a country where physical cash is something of the past. The success stories we read in news articles and international development blog posts accurately describe the prevalence of mobile money, but the use cases they discuss are often derived from the ‘low hanging fruit’—the urban middle class, where mobile money is indeed common, convenient and accessible. What our case study uncovers is the story that’s less often told: that of the struggle, the vast amount of human interaction, motivation and problem-solving required to get mobile money adopted in so-called ‘last-mile’ communities—places where infrastructure, technical capacity and the agent network are weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;essential-learnings&quot;&gt;Essential learnings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-work-is-high-touch&quot;&gt;This work is high-touch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the panel, both Grameen and SIMLab described the vast amount of training and hands-on work that is required to integrate mobile money systems with everyday operations in last-mile organizations. We have seen that the outcome of simply supplying software platforms with little support tends to be misuse, confusion and ultimately a failure to shift systems and sustainably implement new technologies. However, the organizational development work needed to break down barriers to adoption is unfashionable, and contradicts the popular view (and desire) which sees technology innovation as low-cost and exponentially scalable. The organizational development needs of partners are, in our experience, often overlooked and under-budgeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;people-matter&quot;&gt;People matter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motivation, trust, and comfort with change all matter and without tailoring services and training to fulfill the needs of people, adoption will be stifled. SIMLab has had success by identifying and empowering local changemakers who have been able to significantly propel adoption and trust.  A local advocate and peer support network can support organizations and community through change and increase resilience over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;software-is-tough-hardware-is-tough-markets-are-tough&quot;&gt;Software is tough, hardware is tough, markets are tough&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All four panelists spoke to the challenges of the mobile money companies and more broadly, about mobile network operators in frontier markets as being difficult, if not impossible to work with. Sean McDonald described Frontline’s long-term mode of engagement, helping organizations to avoid working directly with mobile network operators (MNOs) by using consumer accounts, effectively, as APIs. The lack of standardization across handset manufacturers and Android operating systems make third-party development an overwhelming challenge here, which likely has an effect on the low number of value-added services (VAS) in the mobile money space, limiting competition to the detriment of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shifting-funding-responsibilities&quot;&gt;Shifting funding responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kay McGowan responded to the question of what can be done to translate success stories of the urban middle class to the last mile, Kay argues that greater support by the public sector is what the last mile needs. Where economic incentive is lacking for MNOs, for example in developing APIs and pushing agent networks out to the last mile, the public sector has a responsibility to step in, to provide the infrastructure, regulations and governance that would stimulate the business lines that have become infrastructure. All panelists echoed Sean’s statement that underserved areas need to be disproportionately supported in the high-touch interventions they require for successful adoption, but that costs money, time and largely, a realization from donors that it’s a priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-just-arent-there-yet-but-its-where-were-heading&quot;&gt;We just aren’t there yet, but it’s where we’re heading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Success stories in tough areas are few and far between, but they are possible and we’re quickly learning what it takes to achieve success in challenging contexts. We are building up the experience and knowledge required to make this type of work more reasonable and effective. We as a sector need to continue to state the problems clearly and voice our disenchantment with the status quo. To those of us on the ground, it may seem like we’re still far from winning—but compared to five years ago we’ve made considerable progress. Success stories in urban areas were front page stories, now they’re commonplace; progress is happening, but it happens in pockets and in waves, and we must continue to demand that funding and time go to vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future&quot;&gt;The future?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us at SIMLab, the Brown Bag Lunch affirmed our approach and conviction that the last mile needs special treatment—and was a fantastic opportunity to share our experiences with the larger development community.  It was reassuring to see we are not the only ones experiencing difficulties in last mile change management, and that these problems are very much on the minds of international organizations many of us in the space. The insights gained on the type of work the development sector needs to push forward in order for us to reach a point where appropriate solutions are available in challenging contexts were promising and seemed tangible.  There are ambitious goals on the horizon of the international development community: the World Bank is aiming at universal financial access by 2020, and to reach this goal international development agencies and development banks are going to have to pay a disproportionate amount of attention to building infrastructure, regulatory conditions and governance in underdeveloped geographies and markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more insights and to hear the discussion for yourself, tune in to our &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/simlab-podcast/id1056814879?mt=2&quot;&gt;iTunes podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/socialimpactlab/only-tough-options-1&quot;&gt;or on Soundcloud!&lt;/a&gt; And don’t forget to let us know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 04:07:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/11/09/mobile-money-in-the-last-mile/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/11/09/mobile-money-in-the-last-mile/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on our ethos for FrontlineSMS&#39; tenth birthday</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy Halloween!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 31st October isn’t just your annual opportunity to eat your weight in sweets - it’s also the official birthday of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com&quot;&gt;FrontlineSMS&lt;/a&gt;, and this year marks the tenth anniversary of its first release!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The award-winning SMS management tool was the core of SIMLab’s work for our first seven years - but the first version of the software was actually released for the first time &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/2011/10/31/back-to-the-future-17-things-you-might-not-know-about-frontlinesms/&quot;&gt;on this day in 2005&lt;/a&gt;. In 2007, Ken Banks, our founder, registered what became Social Impact Lab with the US Internal Revenue Service, as the institutional home to receive the foundation funding that he had raised to build a new website and version 1 of the software. In 2014, we &lt;a href=&quot;http://simlab.org/blog/2014/09/02/welcome-to-SIMLab/&quot;&gt;spun out FrontlineSMS as a new for-profit&lt;/a&gt;, and today they release &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/2015/10/30/the-big-1-o/&quot;&gt;two new tools, focussed on campaigns and emergency reporting&lt;/a&gt;, capping off an amazing first year as a company and celebrating their entry into double digits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined FrontlineSMS in 2010, Ken honoured me and the other staff with a dizzying amount of trust and confidence. He allowed us to embark on an ambitious redesign of the software just weeks after Sean and I started to lead our operations; gave us responsibility for raising funds and developing a new business model; and trusted us from the beginning to represent the organization and the FrontlineSMS ethos at events and with partners. He calls it his ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/2012/05/29/a-transition-announcement-from-our-founder-ken-banks/&quot;&gt;Rolling Stones School of Management&lt;/a&gt;’, and the opportunity it afforded me changed the course of my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the only non-negotiable requirement he had of us all was that we strive every day to fulfill the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/2011/10/17/six-years-on-reinforcing-our-core-values/&quot;&gt;core values&lt;/a&gt; that had informed the FrontlineSMS project from the beginning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Putting users ahead – and at the heart – of everything we do, striving for a positive interaction with anyone who comes into contact with our work, aiming to inspire others whilst respecting a diversity of views, always reaching for better, fostering a positive “anything is possible” attitude, making sure we continue to put people – and their needs – ahead of the aspirations of the tech community, managing expectations both internally and for our users, and finally – constantly reminding ourselves why we do what we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Focus on the users and all else will follow’ was one of the core mantras that I took from my time working directly with Ken. Every day until some time in 2013, I (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Flo_Sci&quot;&gt;Florence&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.me/silakisoso&quot;&gt;Sila&lt;/a&gt;, or Ken himself) would log into our Ning support site, Twitter and Facebook before we checked our email, and the rule was that all support requests got a reply within 24 hours, except at weekends. FrontlineSMS is still notable for its &lt;a href=&quot;https://frontlinecloud.zendesk.com/home&quot;&gt;excellent user support&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past year at SIMLab, it’s been very clear to me how core those values still are to our organization. Instead of being embodied in a software platform, they come through in the projects we take on, the work we put into them, our critiques and conversations; the writing and guides we share, and the commitment of our team, so evident to me every day. Indeed, those values were at the heart of the decision to spin out FrontlineSMS - we felt we could better serve both the users of the software and the partners we worked with if we divided our software development team and our growing consulting and policy practice. At the moment we’re working on a clear written set of principles that will guide our work, which we’ll share on our website along with our strategy for the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this weekend, though, we can look back at ten years of supporting FrontlineSMS users to monitor elections, manage rural health clinics, report environmental damage, safeguard humanitarian teams, and thousands of other use cases in more than 130 countries. And we’ll be raising a glass of something pink to FrontlineSMS and its stellar team!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2015 10:25:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/10/31/frontlines-tenth-birthday/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/10/31/frontlines-tenth-birthday/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learn to use mobile in your work through our online course</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update! We’ve extended the deadline to apply to this Sunday, 4 October. Don’t delay and apply for our course today!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are excited to invite you to submit an application for Social Impact Lab’s upcoming online course, “Scalable, Low-Cost Technologies for Civil Society Organizations”, which will run from 06 October- 24 November 2015. You can apply &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.simlab.org/sign-up/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the third time we’ve run the course, and we have some exciting new features and adjustments, including expanding our language resources and better optimizing the time and formats for low-bandwidth users and working professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-the-course-about&quot;&gt;What is the course about?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course will guide participants through the use of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/technologies/frontlinesms-overview/&quot;&gt;FrontlineSMS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/technologies/frontlinecloud-overview/&quot;&gt;FrontlineCloud&lt;/a&gt;.  Modules focus on using the SMS-based two-way communication platform in your programs, and participants will be directly supported to build a project portfolio of their own submitted work based on course assignments, in around 2-3 hours per week. Other topics include how to design mobile-centered or mobile-enabled projects, risk-mapping, data integrity and ethics considerations when using ICTs and mobile phones in civil society, democracy, transparency, and accountability initiatives. The course is made possible by a grant from the United Nations Democracy Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-is-this-course-for&quot;&gt;Who is this course for?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is designed for people at small and medium organizations, primarily non-profits and NGOs focused on democracy, civic engagement, transparency and accountability. We’ve done our best to optimize the course for low-bandwidth users. However, you will need internet connectivity in order to participate in the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have begun to translate some of the course resources into French! If you have French colleagues who are interested in participating in a group with you, or in watching the technical demos and completing a few resources for the course, please feel free to share with them. We are currently in the process of doing the same for Spanish, and hope to have these available soon as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-the-commitment&quot;&gt;What is the commitment?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will spend about 2-3 hours each week engaging with the platform and materials, with optional online clinic hours offered twice a week for people who want to ask questions in real-time. The course will run for 7 weeks from 06 October- 24 November 2015. The first two modules run for two weeks, since it will take more time to set you up on the software than it will to teach you about new features once you get going. This also allows you to more easily integrate it into your work schedule!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To encourage participation and help cover some of the costs of the course, we’re charging a nominal fee of $50, payable through Paypal (or alternate means if this is not possible for you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-i-apply&quot;&gt;How do I apply?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill out our &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.frontlinesms.com/sign-up/&quot;&gt;registration form&lt;/a&gt; by 4 October. We’ll accept 35-40 participants and will let you know the status of your application on a rolling basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;course-fee&quot;&gt;Course Fee&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If accepted, you will be sent instructions to pay your course fee of $50.00.  Please don’t let cost be an inhibiting factor! We have scholarships available by request, please email &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt; for more details, or request one in your registration form &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.frontlinesms.com/sign-up/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-if-i-have-other-questions&quot;&gt;What if I have other questions?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read about the course in more depth &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.simlab.org/how-it-works/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any additional questions, send us an email at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2015 08:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/09/17/online-course-announcement/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/09/17/online-course-announcement/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Can SMS be used to reach women and girls in new ways in emergencies?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Humanitarian agencies have made increasing use of SMS and mobile telephony in disaster response since the South Asian Tsunami in 2004-5, but particularly following the Haitian earthquake in 2010, where lack of access to communities and high mobile penetration combined to make SMS an attractive means of distributing key messages about sanitation and available assistance. From the last mile rural community to the most vulnerable in urban settings, the predictable cost, asynchronous but intimate nature, and inherent robustness of SMS make it ideal for moving small packets of information swiftly and reliably. In contexts where communication by other means is costly or unreliable, SMS can be effectively used to manage staff and volunteers, collect management information and monitoring data, and provide a responsive two-way communications channel for beneficiaries and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given its potential, can SMS be used to reach women and girls in new ways in emergencies? At present, this is only partially clear—as with much of the existing knowledge about the impact of SMS and mobile in disaster relief, more robust data is required before we understand precisely how this works. In many cases, the nature of women’s interaction with technology makes this difficult to acquire. It’s hard to make basic statements about women’s use of technology in the developing world with great confidence. Women are less likely than men to have the paperwork required to register a SIM card, so their phone may be registered, if not owned and controlled by their male relatives. Women may not have unfettered or unobserved access to handsets, which indeed can be used as instruments of control. For adolescent girls, age is an additional barrier which may make it doubly difficult for them to make use of mobile programs designed to empower them. However, it’s clear that there are potential gains for women and girls in providing mobile access channels to services such as healthcare and nutrition information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In post-Tsunami Batticaloa, Sri Lanka, Minmini News set up an SMS news service for women that attempted to reflect the concerns and experiences of women not covered in the mainstream media. News was sourced, produced and shared by women, for women, to overwhelmingly positive reviews from its users. News information on public services, local emergencies, and women’s experiences, achievements and challenges was collected, fact-checked and written up in text messages by a central ‘news team’ of one or two women and reviewed by an editor. This information was sent out using FrontlineSMS as one to three messages each day. Women who received the messages said that the service had changed their relationship to news and information, and mitigated some of the social challenges women experienced in getting and sharing news through normal channels. One woman, displaced and maltreated, was found and brought home as a direct result of information shared via the service. Minmini News has not yet reported its longer-term impacts, and no age-disaggregated data was collected, so there is no way to understand whether the particular needs and concerns of adolescent girls were met through the initiative. However, examples like Yoza, a South African mLiteracy project, show the potential power of engaging young people, including girls, through mobile-based interventions, even in resource-constrained contexts like urban slums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other communications platform, effective use of SMS requires careful context assessment and an understanding of if and how SMS is routinely used by a population. Where SMS use is inhibited by cultural and technical factors, as in southern Pakistan, it is far better to use communications tools that already work for the community. In the 2010 southern Pakistan floods, aid agencies fresh from the Haiti response and remembering the successful use of SMS in the NWFP (North-West Frontier Province) in Pakistan’s 2008 post-conflict displacement were surprised to note almost no use of SMS by the local population. This was due to low literacy levels, and also because the local dialect was written in a script whose character set wasn’t present on most cellphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding all this through a gendered, age-sensitive lens requires closer, more qualitative analysis. What is clear, is that women will experience all the same barriers to mobile phone access and using SMS as men, but often to a greater degree, and in some cases, young women and girls most of all. Literacy is an obvious limiting factor for SMS use—and women and girls are less likely to be literate than men and boys—although proximate literacy (where the recipient takes the SMS to someone who reads to understand the message), functional literacy (where the recipient can successfully interpret a familiar message, such as a mobile money notification) and the run-and-tell model, where one literate member of a community receives a message and spreads the word, are all able to circumvent this challenge to a degree. Disability and infirmity may make SMS hard to read and access, so they may not be appropriate for older people, who may be less aware of or less likely to adopt new technologies. Lack of access to handsets and electricity may inhibit cellphone use altogether, and women are less likely to own and control their own phone than men. Access to power is a major financial and infrastructural challenge. Women’s incomes are lower and in some areas people spend as much money on powering their phones as on airtime. In a crisis, this disposable income is the first thing to go, coupled with the fact that access to power if communities are displaced is not a given. Travel, which is often required to get a signal or electricity to charge handsets in rural areas, is more difficult for women and girls. Finally, cultural factors may inhibit SMS use. Gender roles may mean that such a link to the public world, or owning and controlling technology in this way, is not considered appropriate or necessary for women. This is particularly challenging for girls, where elders may have concerns around the sexualisation, or sometimes the Westernization, of young women exposed to information via the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agencies need to carefully consider the opportunities and challenges inherent in using mobile for women in emergencies. It seems that while there may be initial hurdles to overcome, once women are able to make the case for access to technology and learn how to best use it for their advantage, the potential is enormous for their opportunistic use of information to improve their lives and those of their families. Agencies will still need to avoid pitfalls—messages relating to family planning or access to cash grants need careful consideration in the same way that analogue delivery would, and we cannot make assumptions about the degree of privacy women and girls have on their handsets. Considering young women, for whom both age and gender may act as barriers to access to technology and information, requires an additional depth of enquiry into social behavior and cultural norms that may be only partly articulated and understood. But in this context, a more long-term, community-oriented approach, where SMS is used as an easy interaction channel to foster community ownership of programs and open feedback about the work, may allay fear and suspicion and help women to improve the resilience of their entire community to disaster, through mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 06:22:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/09/08/sms-emergencies/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/09/08/sms-emergencies/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mobile Money in the Last Mile of Kenya</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Brookings Institute’s Financial and Digital Inclusion Project named Kenya as the top scoring country in the world for financial inclusion based on country commitment, mobile capacity, regulatory environment and adoption of traditional and digital financial services. Yet, SIMLab’s efforts to introduce to mobile money to organizations in rural Kenya have encountered significant barriers to adoption and sustained use by organizations and end-users alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we are releasing our case study, &lt;a href=&quot;/files/SIMLab Case Study - Mobile money in the last mile.pdf&quot;&gt;Implementing a Mobile Money Management Tool and Training Approach in the Last Mile&lt;/a&gt;, which reviews our experience implementing a mobile money software tool in rural Kenya, for a project cofunded by UK Department for International Development (DFID) through the Global Poverty Action Fund (GPAF). The project worked with 40 NGOs and SACCOs (Savings and Credit Cooperatives) in rural Kenya to make the transition from cash to mobile money in a country where 90% of households have used mobile money services. Despite this, we found that last-mile organizations are not simply awaiting a platform that suits their technical needs to incorporate digital cash into their daily business activities. Rather, complex human, organizational and environmental challenges raise serious questions about the ‘build it, and they will come’ philosophy that has driven much of the mMoney space over the last ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To discuss this case study and the challenges that others have faced in the space, we are hosting an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eventbrite.com/e/introducing-mobile-money-to-organizations-in-the-last-mile-in-kenya-tickets-18356055456&quot;&gt;event&lt;/a&gt; today, September 4th, at the OpenGovHub in Washington DC. If you’re in DC, you can come by, or you can follow us on Twitter, where @SIMLab will be tweeting about it under the hashtag #lastmilemoney. We also have limited slots for a live-streaming webinar, which you can RSVP for at the above link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to Kelly Church, SIMLab’s Project Director, the event will also feature Leo Tobias, Technology Team Manager at Grameen Foundation, presenting on their work in Uganda; Sean McDonald, CEO of FrontlineSMS, reflecting on the very real obstacles caused by fractured operator, handset and software markets; and Kay McGowan, Digital Finance Team Lead at USAID, who will offer her reflections and responses to the panelists’ presentations, and share some of the direction of USAID policy as the mMoney field approaches its ninth year. Together the panel will hopefully shed light on mobile money efforts within and beyond Kenya, and look critically at what is being done and what needs to be done at the technology and policy level to ensure the next five years will bring greater, more widespread and engaged adoption of mobile financial services.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 10:25:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/09/04/mobile-money-in-the-last-mile-of-kenya/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/09/04/mobile-money-in-the-last-mile-of-kenya/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building A Better Everything</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In June, I had the opportunity to participate on a panel at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cyberjustice.ca/en/&quot;&gt;University of Montreal’s Cyberjustice Lab&lt;/a&gt;. I chatted about how we use our mission and values to inform our day-to-day work, and felt it might be helpful to put some of what I talked about in writing, to help explain just what it is that we do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SIMLab works to make systems and services more accessible, responsive, and resilient. Talking to lawyers, traditionally service providers, I like to focus my framing on legal systems, to help people think a little differently. Put simply, a system has inputs and outputs that feed back into each other. These inputs and outputs can be information, behavior, money, time, widgets…and so on. So, if our mission is to improve systems, it means we measure the success of our technology projects by whether it makes a system better. (We also have to draw lines around what the system is for a given project, but that’s a topic for another day.) Our values, accessibility, responsiveness, and resilience, are how we define what “better” looks like in a system, and illuminate lessons that inform how we approach our work. So how do we think about each of those values in a more practical sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring accessibility sounds simple: how easy is it for someone to get into a system? But sometimes this manifests in interesting ways: with the DC Public Library, we’re &lt;a href=&quot;http://simlab.org/blog/2015/05/21/first-resort&quot;&gt;working&lt;/a&gt; to help librarians deliver better information about social services, so that people can navigate the system more easily. As with any project we do, we’ve dedicated lots of time to exploring the context—here, the DC social services ecosystem—to test and revise (and revise again) our hypotheses, and embrace the limitations of the project—here, that there’s an opportunity to provide help without doing a full social work intake interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If accessibility is about getting in to the system, responsiveness might be what the system produces. This isn’t always improving the substance of an outcome—after all, not everyone can be happy with the outcome of a legal case—sometimes it’s simply making a system more efficient. In Odisha, India, we’re &lt;a href=&quot;http://simlab.org/blog/2015/07/23/paper-houses-digital-homes/&quot;&gt;working&lt;/a&gt; with Landesa to make it easier for supervisors and potential titleholders alike to coordinate and track a complex surveying and land titling program. Although we’re building technology, ultimately our hope is to make humans more responsive. As a result, we strive to understand who we’re creating more—or less—work for, and constantly monitor what we’ve built to see if it’s working. In other words, to build a more responsive system, we need to be responsive, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resilience is perhaps the fuzziest-seeming value of the three. I like to describe it helping systems (and organizations) be self-propelled. So, are we helping a system—or an organization—adapt to shocks, or changes in the bigger system around it? We work with non-profits on small engagements to help them use a piece of technology better, whether it’s improving how they collect feedback from people calling a help line, creating a reminder system for clients, or connecting with clients over a different communications channel, such as SMS. Whether the project is big or small, our goal is that at the end of the day, it can run without our help, and adapt to the inevitable changes that an organization or a system will face. Resilient technologies can help make resilient organizations, and in turn, more resilient systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter where we work, we try to be inclusive, foster local ownership of technology, encourage good habits, generate data, and make complex processes more efficient and transparent. This isn’t always easy: systems are chaotic and messy. So, in our work, we value fluidity: how well our work fills the gaps in a system, and how well it adapts (and we adapt) to change. Because systems never stop: the flow of information, of demand for services, of need for help, is constant and unceasing, whether you’re ready to handle it or not. In that blur of motion, we think it’s critical that systems are accessible, responsive, and resilient—even if those values are hard to define, and harder to measure. As Donella Meadows, a pioneer of systems thinking, put it, “No one can define or measure justice, democracy, security, freedom, truth, or love. No one can define or measure any value. But if no one speaks up for them, if systems aren’t designed to produce them, if we don’t speak about them and point toward their presence or absence, they will cease to exist.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2015 05:07:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/08/28/building-a-better-everything/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/08/28/building-a-better-everything/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Paper Houses, Digital Homes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“All the land records against this wall have been scanned.” Stacks of land records—browning paper tied together with string—lined the walls, the tables, the shelves. White receipts with markered labels flopped out of some of them; processed and scanned. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tahasildar&quot;&gt;tahasildar&lt;/a&gt; beamed, visibly proud at the progress his office had made. Still, stacks of titles remained, and still more remained unrecorded. And any new records would also be delivered on paper, awaiting digitization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the state of land records in Odisha, India—and many other maturing land regimes: digital, almost. An ever-changing mix of analog and digital record-keeping further complicates the delivery of titles to landless homes. The closer one gets to a household-level record, the more likely that record is only exist on paper. The household and village level is also where tracking is most critical—not only for administrators to understand what’s working and what isn’t, but to create a transparent record of activity that potential titleholders can use to mark their own progress through a complicated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: auto; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/xIXGZgJKfT/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Piles of land records.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A photo posted by Keith Porcaro (@vigilantballoon) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2014-12-28T00:41:06+00:00&quot;&gt;Dec 27, 2014 at 4:41pm PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If information about a titling process can be made digital, in whatever form is available, that can have a transformative effect not only on how efficiently land titles are delivered to the most marginalized, but on how people understand and build their lives around land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Odisha, SIMLab has partnered with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landesa.org&quot;&gt;Landesa&lt;/a&gt; on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.org&quot;&gt;Google.org&lt;/a&gt; funded project to do just that. We’re using simple mobile technology (SMS and &lt;a href=&quot;http://frontlinesms.com&quot;&gt;FrontlineCloud&lt;/a&gt;, to start) to help deliver titles to landless rural and tribal villagers across Odisha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last year, SIMLab staff have spent nearly three months on the ground in Odisha: interviewing officials at every stage of the land process, visiting villages that have received title under the program, conducting context assessments, iteratively designing and modifying the software in close consultation with Landesa staff, and conducting technology trainings across the state. Along the way, we’ve adjusted the program and approach to the changing context in Odisha: adjusting the scope of the program to fit technology ownership in villages and districts, reintroducing ourself to a new set of government officials after the most recent round of elections, and iterating a scaling program to meet the exciting e-governance developments in Odisha. That’s not even mentioning the cyclone that swept the state last October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, we began the first round of training and implementation, and continue to monitor the pilot for results. For the pilot stage, officials and village-level workers can use SMS to report their progress (there are nearly 30 individual steps in the program, taking between 12 and 18 months to complete in total) and receive reminders of tasks that are behind schedule, while supervisors can generate and download up to the minute aggregate reports, summarizing total progress in their area. Finally, village-level officials, and villagers, can submit status queries to find out how far along their—or any—village is in the program. Because the system uses a combination of SMS and cloud-based services, we can adjust the parameters of the system (such as the number of days before a task is considered late) mid-stream. In other words, rather than replacing a process that’s already underway, we’ve created a low-touch system that allows select data to run ahead of paper surveys, hopefully reducing the latency between problem identification and problem solving from months to days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re excited about what lies ahead for this program, and for others like it. Although the technology context is difficult, we’re exploring small opportunities to reach out directly to titleholders, enabling a person to track their own application, build land literacy, or even request services via SMS. We’re also beginning to explore integration into the rapidly maturing Odisha land database, which would enable government officials to seamlessly communicate land-record changes to the local level, villagers to verify title, and perhaps open up an opportunity to communicate private land transactions back to a database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To show how SMS and other inclusive technologies can be used to optimize large-scale land interventions, we’ve made a small demo, which will be up for a short time. You can access it by texting the word DEMO to ‭+1 (919) 582-5077. If you’re interested in working with SIMLab to bring inclusive technology to your land program, shoot us an email, at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#107;&amp;#101;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#104;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#107;&amp;#101;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#104;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 10:43:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/07/23/paper-houses-digital-homes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/07/23/paper-houses-digital-homes/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open First, Ask Later: Rethinking Data Ethics Among International Agencies, Donors, and NGOs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Aggregating and opening data presents opportunities for deepening civic engagement, addressing decades-long environmental coordination challenges, or highlighting inefficient institutional processes and procedures, among many other potential uses, benefits and information gains. The same data, branded as a public good, is also the subject of many debates regarding risks, agency, and privacy among others. There is a rising need to sort out the ethics of use and power dynamics over decision-making when it comes to open/ing data for ‘development’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2013, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.d4d.orange.com/en/home&quot;&gt;Data for Development Challenge&lt;/a&gt; (D4D), a challenge run by mobile network operator Orange, opens mobile phone usage data up to researchers selected to analyze it,  in order to facilitate the use of big data in key development sectors, defined in conjunction with government ministries and organizations (for example, the D4D Senegal Challenge focuses on health, agriculture, transport/urban planning, energy, and national statistics). There is an additional category, defined by Orange themselves for those “advancing anonymisation techniques to allow sharing of data that is relevant for society while respecting privacy. A constructive dialogue with the Personal Data Commission was opened up at the start of the project, focused, in part, to work on the creation of robust sharing formats and exploration of the uses and limitations of the synthetic data sets.” In 2013, the European Union committed to implementing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/open-data-charter/g8-open-data-charter-and-technical-annex&quot;&gt;G8 Open Data Charter&lt;/a&gt;, which outlines five principles for government data: open government data by default; release as much data as possible (quantity) and then improve as needed (quality); usable by all- free, easy to access, open formats; release data for improved governance- transparency about processes and sharing of lessons learned with other governments; and release data for innovation- encourage use of open data in civil society. The EU’s open data commitments cover all grants provided by EU donor and development agencies. USAID announced its &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.usaid.gov/2014/10/announcing-usaids-open-data-policy/&quot;&gt;Open Data Policy&lt;/a&gt; in 2014, which commits all partners and subcontractors to submit any and all USAID-funded data, again open by default “with limited exceptions,” in a standardized format to their Development Data Library, tagging with relevant labels to facilitate metadata and consumer use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each of these cases, “opening” data represents a continuum of principles, commitments, processes, and actions related to generating, organizing and sharing [and making decisions based on] information. The rapid adoption of open standards would signal their promise, and has in many ways enabled and accelerated its momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International organizations (non-governmental, multilateral, and bilateral) aren’t unique because of the data they work with, but because they play a unique, and often unclear role in civic, social, political, and economic life around the world - with a particularly heavy presence in conflict-affected countries and countries in transition. The number of NGOs alone operating in active conflict areas has grown exponentially in the past 30 years.  According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.versobooks.com/books/532-the-least-of-all-possible-evils&quot;&gt;Weizman&lt;/a&gt;, “while in 1980 there were about 40 NGOs dealing with the Ethiopian famine, a decade later 250 were operating during the Yugoslavian war; by 2004, 2,500 were involved in Afghanistan.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growing imperative among international agencies, donors, and organizations to open first and ask later needs rethinking. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IOs are represented and play a role in highly sensitive, transitional or conflict-affected environments, where risks and considerations around the collection of information that is linked to an individual, even if not about that individual have different implications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The legitimacy of international organizations’ presence, projects, and services is often derived from other international bodies, and accountability requirements are most focused on populations in countries where organizations are headquartered. How people in different countries, individually or collectively, interact with, consent to, and/or share opinions related to international organizations and institutions is by no means uniform, where present at all, unless there is a particular evaluation underway and a dedicated staff person is deployed to collect it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a higher concentration of uncoordinated, and frequently evolving efforts, resulting in duplicated efforts and survey and research fatigue.  All the fragmented data associated with different initiatives, that may be de-identified by an individual organization and seem innocuous as reported, has the potential for meta-analysis which doesn’t rely on individual details.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The regulations and policies regarding data vary widely between countries, and it is unclear which country’s standards take precedent or apply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where standards and protocols are unclear, program staff or field office directors often make the call.  When there are standards imposed on situations for which they simply do not fit, meeting reporting obligations may take priority without clear knowledge of logic or consequences associated with decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IOs are accountable to a wide number of stakeholders, with the population they seek to serve, represent, or research coming in at the bottom of the list. They must often report to their headquarters, most likely located in another country, host governments, and donor(s).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the volume of organizations growing alongside the volume of data being produced or opened through their actions or advocacy, questions about ethical data use, protocols, and standards quickly become daunting in their sheer volume; making them all the more necessary to ask at all levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SIMLab has benefited greatly from the work that others are doing on this topic and our own work in the past, including a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/frontlinesms_userguide.pdf&quot;&gt;data integrity guide&lt;/a&gt;, focused on data ethics when using low-end mobile technologies, published in 2011.  In the coming months, SIMLab will continue taking stock of data ethics questions and approaches in international organizations, as open data and data-driven decision-making, accelerate into accepted, even expected, standards.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 06:22:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/06/03/open-data/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/06/03/open-data/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>First Resort: Building social services resources at DC Public Library</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the wide range of social and legal services available in American cities, it’s not always easy for a person to find the right service provider—or often, set of providers—who can help. Service providers, from lawyers to social workers to case managers, have deep expertise helping people solve problems, but sometimes, it may not be obvious that someone should, say, call a lawyer in addition to a food bank if they receive a letter that food stamp benefits have been cut off.  A single story may require the help of multiple experts, and multiple services, in order to meet a person’s need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly for those on the wrong side of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S4O0MK0ZDRE&quot;&gt;digital divide&lt;/a&gt;, people often turn to the library for information on where to find help. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclibrary.org&quot;&gt;DC Public Library&lt;/a&gt; (DCPL) is working to better meet this need, by improving how it provides recommendations and resources on social services in the city, and equipping librarians with question-and-answer tools that can help draw out other services that a person might need. We’re excited to announce that—with support from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.knightfoundation.org/funding-initiatives/knight-prototype-fund/&quot;&gt;Knight Foundation’s Prototype Fund&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://openreferral.org&quot;&gt;Open Referral Initiative&lt;/a&gt;—SIMLab is partnering with DCPL to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is, in some ways, new territory for us as well—it’s one of our first hands-on projects in the United States—and so, in close collaboration with the Library, we’ve been working hard over the past weeks to get a sense of the world we’re working in. We’ve interviewed front-line librarians to better understand the types of services people seek at the library, and the stories people tell when they do so. For this prototype, we wanted to narrow our focus to a subset of services, so we could explore more deeply within that subset and test our hypotheses and assumptions on a smaller scale. We’ve chosen to focus on on services for the elderly, a commonly requested service set at the library. The difficulty of finding elderly services is a microcosm of finding services generally: after all, most everyone gets old eventually, and many people are navigating the system for the first time, often in search of help for an aging parent, family member, or partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spring, SIMLab and DCPL team members have spent time together exploring the elderly services available in DC. City agencies and service providers alike have generously shared their time and experience with us, helping us to learn about some of the intake, referral, and capacity challenges that their organizations face, as well as technology tools that are currently in development to help meet those challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: auto; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/2ooOrvJKUb/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Working with DCPL to build paper prototypes to help people find social services in DC.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A photo posted by Keith Porcaro (@vigilantballoon) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2015-05-13T20:03:27+00:00&quot;&gt;May 13, 2015 at 1:03pm PDT&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, we’re trying to bridge the gap between a person’s story of need and the help they are seeking, or might need to seek. With librarians and social workers, we’re helping to identify questions librarians can ask to help clarify and illuminate a person’s situation. So, a request that starts with “I need daytime care for my aging parent” might yield a collection of immediate and long-term resources, from case managers and agencies who can do complete assessments to wellness and activity programs available now. We aren’t turning the library into an intake center, but trying to use technology and research to help people navigate the natural peculiarities of a complex system (like the same service having different names, depending on the provider).  We’re also helping DCPL think about how this tool might practically be deployed in a library branch, from the trainings librarians will need, to how to create a safe space where these questions can be asked, and ways to get anonymous feedback on the information provided. All the while, we’ll be focused on learning—what we’ve done well, what we can do better, what needs are yet to be met—and documenting and sharing that learning so that others can build on and replicate our work in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is a prototype, we’re excited about exploring these dynamics over the long-term, and on finding creative ways to help organizations use technology and work together to solve tricky problems. We’re in early days yet, but watch this space and others for more on what we learn. We’re slowly exploring challenges in the United States that we might be able to help with, from getting feedback on service referrals to reaching offline and low-literacy communities. If you’ve got a project that you think SIMLab might be a fit for, &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;reach out to us&lt;/a&gt;; we’d love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 06:22:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/05/21/first-resort/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/05/21/first-resort/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sign up for our upcoming course on using mobile for CSOs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We are excited to open applications for Social Impact Lab’s upcoming online course, “Scalable, Low-Cost Technologies for Civil Society Organizations”, which will run from 24 February- 5 May 2015. You can apply &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.frontlinesms.com/sign-up/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-course-about&quot;&gt;What is the course about?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course will guide participants through the use of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/technologies/frontlinesms-overview/&quot;&gt;FrontlineSMS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/technologies/frontlinecloud-overview/&quot;&gt;FrontlineCloud&lt;/a&gt;.  Modules focus on using the SMS-based two-way communication platform in your programs, and participants will be directly supported to build a project portfolio of their own submitted work based on course assignments, in around 2-3 hours per week. Other topics include how to design mobile-centered or mobile-enabled projects, risk-mapping, data integrity and ethics considerations when using ICTs and mobile phones in civil society, democracy, transparency, and accountability initiatives. The course is made possible by a grant from the United Nations Democracy Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-is-this-course-for&quot;&gt;Who is this course for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is designed for people at small and medium organizations, primarily non-profits and NGOs focused on democracy, civic engagement, transparency and accountability. We’ve done our best to optimize the course for low-bandwidth users. However, you will need internet connectivity in order to participate in the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-commitment&quot;&gt;What is the commitment?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will spend about 2-3 hours each week engaging with the platform and materials, with optional online clinic hours offered twice a week for people who want to ask questions in real-time. The course will run for 10 weeks, with 2 weeks for each module to accommodate busy working schedules, from 24 February-5 May 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To encourage participation and help cover some of the costs of the course, we’re charging a nominal fee of $50, payable through Paypal (or alternate means if this is not possible for you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-i-apply&quot;&gt;How do I apply?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill out our &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.frontlinesms.com/sign-up/&quot;&gt;registration form&lt;/a&gt; by 13 February. We’ll accept 35-40 participants and will let you know the status of your application by 18 February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;course-fee&quot;&gt;Course Fee&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If accepted, you will be sent a link to our PayPal account to pay your course fee of $50.00.  If you need an alternative payment arrangement, or to request a scholarship, please email &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-if-i-have-other-questions&quot;&gt;What if I have other questions?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read about the course in more depth &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.frontlinesms.com/how-it-works/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any additional questions, send us an email at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2015 09:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://simlab.org/blog/2015/02/02/sign-up-for-our-upcoming-course/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simlab.org/blog/2015/02/02/sign-up-for-our-upcoming-course/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
