<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Impact Lab</title>
    <description>We are Social Impact Lab. We use inclusive technologies to build systems and services that are more accessible, responsive, and resilient.</description>
    <link>/simlabrefresh/</link>
    <atom:link href="/simlabrefresh/simlabrefresh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 16:03:14 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 16:03:14 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Paper Houses, Digital Homes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“All the land records against this wall have been scanned.” Stacks of land records—browning paper tied together with string—lined the walls, the tables, the shelves. White receipts with markered labels flopped out of some of them; processed and scanned. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tahasildar&quot;&gt;tahasildar&lt;/a&gt; beamed, visibly proud at the progress his office had made. Still, stacks of titles remained, and still more remained unrecorded. And any new records would also be delivered on paper, awaiting digitization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the state of land records in Odisha, India—and many other maturing land regimes: digital, almost. An ever-changing mix of analog and digital record-keeping further complicates the delivery of titles to landless homes. The closer one gets to a household-level record, the more likely that record is only exist on paper. The household and village level is also where tracking is most critical—not only for administrators to understand what’s working and what isn’t, but to create a transparent record of activity that potential titleholders can use to mark their own progress through a complicated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: auto; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/xIXGZgJKfT/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Piles of land records.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A photo posted by Keith Porcaro (@vigilantballoon) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2014-12-28T00:41:06+00:00&quot;&gt;Dec 27, 2014 at 4:41pm PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If information about a titling process can be made digital, in whatever form is available, that can have a transformative effect not only on how efficiently land titles are delivered to the most marginalized, but on how people understand and build their lives around land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Odisha, SIMLab has partnered with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landesa.org&quot;&gt;Landesa&lt;/a&gt; on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.org&quot;&gt;Google.org&lt;/a&gt; funded project to do just that. We’re using simple mobile technology (SMS and &lt;a href=&quot;http://frontlinesms.com&quot;&gt;FrontlineCloud&lt;/a&gt;, to start) to help deliver titles to landless rural and tribal villagers across Odisha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last year, SIMLab staff have spent nearly three months on the ground in Odisha: interviewing officials at every stage of the land process, visiting villages that have received title under the program, conducting context assessments, iteratively designing and modifying the software in close consultation with Landesa staff, and conducting technology trainings across the state. Along the way, we’ve adjusted the program and approach to the changing context in Odisha: adjusting the scope of the program to fit technology ownership in villages and districts, reintroducing ourself to a new set of government officials after the most recent round of elections, and iterating a scaling program to meet the exciting e-governance developments in Odisha. That’s not even mentioning the cyclone that swept the state last October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, we began the first round of training and implementation, and continue to monitor the pilot for results. For the pilot stage, officials and village-level workers can use SMS to report their progress (there are nearly 30 individual steps in the program, taking between 12 and 18 months to complete in total) and receive reminders of tasks that are behind schedule, while supervisors can generate and download up to the minute aggregate reports, summarizing total progress in their area. Finally, village-level officials, and villagers, can submit status queries to find out how far along their—or any—village is in the program. Because the system uses a combination of SMS and cloud-based services, we can adjust the parameters of the system (such as the number of days before a task is considered late) mid-stream. In other words, rather than replacing a process that’s already underway, we’ve created a low-touch system that allows select data to run ahead of paper surveys, hopefully reducing the latency between problem identification and problem solving from months to days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re excited about what lies ahead for this program, and for others like it. Although the technology context is difficult, we’re exploring small opportunities to reach out directly to titleholders, enabling a person to track their own application, build land literacy, or even request services via SMS. We’re also beginning to explore integration into the rapidly maturing Odisha land database, which would enable government officials to seamlessly communicate land-record changes to the local level, villagers to verify title, and perhaps open up an opportunity to communicate private land transactions back to a database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To show how SMS and other inclusive technologies can be used to optimize large-scale land interventions, we’ve made a small demo, which will be up for a short time. You can access it by texting the word DEMO to ‭+1 (919) 582-5077. If you’re interested in working with SIMLab to bring inclusive technology to your land program, shoot us an email, at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#107;&amp;#101;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#104;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#107;&amp;#101;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#104;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 10:43:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/07/23/paper-houses-digital-homes</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/07/23/paper-houses-digital-homes</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open First, Ask Later</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Aggregating and opening data presents opportunities for deepening civic engagement, addressing decades-long environmental coordination challenges, or highlighting inefficient institutional processes and procedures, among many other potential uses, benefits and information gains. The same data, branded as a public good, is also the subject of many debates regarding risks, agency, and privacy among others. There is a rising need to sort out the ethics of use and power dynamics over decision-making when it comes to open/ing data for ‘development’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2013, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.d4d.orange.com/en/home&quot;&gt;Data for Development Challenge&lt;/a&gt; (D4D), a challenge run by mobile network operator Orange, opens mobile phone usage data up to researchers selected to analyze it,  in order to facilitate the use of big data in key development sectors, defined in conjunction with government ministries and organizations (for example, the D4D Senegal Challenge focuses on health, agriculture, transport/urban planning, energy, and national statistics). There is an additional category, defined by Orange themselves for those “advancing anonymisation techniques to allow sharing of data that is relevant for society while respecting privacy. A constructive dialogue with the Personal Data Commission was opened up at the start of the project, focused, in part, to work on the creation of robust sharing formats and exploration of the uses and limitations of the synthetic data sets.” In 2013, the European Union committed to implementing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/open-data-charter/g8-open-data-charter-and-technical-annex&quot;&gt;G8 Open Data Charter&lt;/a&gt;, which outlines five principles for government data: open government data by default; release as much data as possible (quantity) and then improve as needed (quality); usable by all- free, easy to access, open formats; release data for improved governance- transparency about processes and sharing of lessons learned with other governments; and release data for innovation- encourage use of open data in civil society. The EU’s open data commitments cover all grants provided by EU donor and development agencies. USAID announced its &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.usaid.gov/2014/10/announcing-usaids-open-data-policy/&quot;&gt;Open Data Policy&lt;/a&gt; in 2014, which commits all partners and subcontractors to submit any and all USAID-funded data, again open by default “with limited exceptions,” in a standardized format to their Development Data Library, tagging with relevant labels to facilitate metadata and consumer use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each of these cases, “opening” data represents a continuum of principles, commitments, processes, and actions related to generating, organizing and sharing [and making decisions based on] information. The rapid adoption of open standards would signal their promise, and has in many ways enabled and accelerated its momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International organizations (non-governmental, multilateral, and bilateral) aren’t unique because of the data they work with, but because they play a unique, and often unclear role in civic, social, political, and economic life around the world - with a particularly heavy presence in conflict-affected countries and countries in transition. The number of NGOs alone operating in active conflict areas has grown exponentially in the past 30 years.  According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.versobooks.com/books/532-the-least-of-all-possible-evils&quot;&gt;Weizman&lt;/a&gt;, “while in 1980 there were about 40 NGOs dealing with the Ethiopian famine, a decade later 250 were operating during the Yugoslavian war; by 2004, 2,500 were involved in Afghanistan.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growing imperative among international agencies, donors, and organizations to open first and ask later needs rethinking. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IOs are represented and play a role in highly sensitive, transitional or conflict-affected environments, where risks and considerations around the collection of information that is linked to an individual, even if not about that individual have different implications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The legitimacy of international organizations’ presence, projects, and services is often derived from other international bodies, and accountability requirements are most focused on populations in countries where organizations are headquartered. How people in different countries, individually or collectively, interact with, consent to, and/or share opinions related to international organizations and institutions is by no means uniform, where present at all, unless there is a particular evaluation underway and a dedicated staff person is deployed to collect it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a higher concentration of uncoordinated, and frequently evolving efforts, resulting in duplicated efforts and survey and research fatigue.  All the fragmented data associated with different initiatives, that may be de-identified by an individual organization and seem innocuous as reported, has the potential for meta-analysis which doesn’t rely on individual details.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The regulations and policies regarding data vary widely between countries, and it is unclear which country’s standards take precedent or apply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where standards and protocols are unclear, program staff or field office directors often make the call.  When there are standards imposed on situations for which they simply do not fit, meeting reporting obligations may take priority without clear knowledge of logic or consequences associated with decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IOs are accountable to a wide number of stakeholders, with the population they seek to serve, represent, or research coming in at the bottom of the list. They must often report to their headquarters, most likely located in another country, host governments, and donor(s).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the volume of organizations growing alongside the volume of data being produced or opened through their actions or advocacy, questions about ethical data use, protocols, and standards quickly become daunting in their sheer volume; making them all the more necessary to ask at all levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SIMLab has benefited greatly from the work that others are doing on this topic and our own work in the past, including a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/frontlinesms_userguide.pdf&quot;&gt;data integrity guide&lt;/a&gt;, focused on data ethics when using low-end mobile technologies, published in 2011.  In the coming months, SIMLab will continue taking stock of data ethics questions and approaches in international organizations, as open data and data-driven decision-making, accelerate into accepted, even expected, standards.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 06:22:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/06/03/open-data</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/06/03/open-data</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>First Resort</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the wide range of social and legal services available in American cities, it’s not always easy for a person to find the right service provider—or often, set of providers—who can help. Service providers, from lawyers to social workers to case managers, have deep expertise helping people solve problems, but sometimes, it may not be obvious that someone should, say, call a lawyer in addition to a food bank if they receive a letter that food stamp benefits have been cut off.  A single story may require the help of multiple experts, and multiple services, in order to meet a person’s need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly for those on the wrong side of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S4O0MK0ZDRE&quot;&gt;digital divide&lt;/a&gt;, people often turn to the library for information on where to find help. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclibrary.org&quot;&gt;DC Public Library&lt;/a&gt; (DCPL) is working to better meet this need, by improving how it provides recommendations and resources on social services in the city, and equipping librarians with question-and-answer tools that can help draw out other services that a person might need. We’re excited to announce that—with support from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.knightfoundation.org/funding-initiatives/knight-prototype-fund/&quot;&gt;Knight Foundation’s Prototype Fund&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://openreferral.org&quot;&gt;Open Referral Initiative&lt;/a&gt;—SIMLab is partnering with DCPL to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is, in some ways, new territory for us as well—it’s one of our first hands-on projects in the United States—and so, in close collaboration with the Library, we’ve been working hard over the past weeks to get a sense of the world we’re working in. We’ve interviewed front-line librarians to better understand the types of services people seek at the library, and the stories people tell when they do so. For this prototype, we wanted to narrow our focus to a subset of services, so we could explore more deeply within that subset and test our hypotheses and assumptions on a smaller scale. We’ve chosen to focus on on services for the elderly, a commonly requested service set at the library. The difficulty of finding elderly services is a microcosm of finding services generally: after all, most everyone gets old eventually, and many people are navigating the system for the first time, often in search of help for an aging parent, family member, or partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spring, SIMLab and DCPL team members have spent time together exploring the elderly services available in DC. City agencies and service providers alike have generously shared their time and experience with us, helping us to learn about some of the intake, referral, and capacity challenges that their organizations face, as well as technology tools that are currently in development to help meet those challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 20px auto; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(/simlabrefreshdata:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/simlabrefreshhttps://instagram.com/p/2ooOrvJKUb/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Working with DCPL to build paper prototypes to help people find social services in DC.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A photo posted by Keith Porcaro (@vigilantballoon) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2015-05-13T20:03:27+00:00&quot;&gt;May 13, 2015 at 1:03pm PDT&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/simlabrefresh//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, we’re trying to bridge the gap between a person’s story of need and the help they are seeking, or might need to seek. With librarians and social workers, we’re helping to identify questions librarians can ask to help clarify and illuminate a person’s situation. So, a request that starts with “I need daytime care for my aging parent” might yield a collection of immediate and long-term resources, from case managers and agencies who can do complete assessments to wellness and activity programs available now. We aren’t turning the library into an intake center, but trying to use technology and research to help people navigate the natural peculiarities of a complex system (like the same service having different names, depending on the provider).  We’re also helping DCPL think about how this tool might practically be deployed in a library branch, from the trainings librarians will need, to how to create a safe space where these questions can be asked, and ways to get anonymous feedback on the information provided. All the while, we’ll be focused on learning—what we’ve done well, what we can do better, what needs are yet to be met—and documenting and sharing that learning so that others can build on and replicate our work in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is a prototype, we’re excited about exploring these dynamics over the long-term, and on finding creative ways to help organizations use technology and work together to solve tricky problems. We’re in early days yet, but watch this space and others for more on what we learn. We’re slowly exploring challenges in the United States that we might be able to help with, from getting feedback on service referrals to reaching offline and low-literacy communities. If you’ve got a project that you think SIMLab might be a fit for, &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;reach out to us&lt;/a&gt;; we’d love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 06:22:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/05/21/first-resort</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/05/21/first-resort</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sign up for our upcoming course on using mobile for CSOs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We are excited to open applications for Social Impact Lab’s upcoming online course, “Scalable, Low-Cost Technologies for Civil Society Organizations”, which will run from 24 February- 5 May 2015. You can apply &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.frontlinesms.com/sign-up/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-course-about&quot;&gt;What is the course about?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course will guide participants through the use of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/technologies/frontlinesms-overview/&quot;&gt;FrontlineSMS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/technologies/frontlinecloud-overview/&quot;&gt;FrontlineCloud&lt;/a&gt;.  Modules focus on using the SMS-based two-way communication platform in your programs, and participants will be directly supported to build a project portfolio of their own submitted work based on course assignments, in around 2-3 hours per week. Other topics include how to design mobile-centered or mobile-enabled projects, risk-mapping, data integrity and ethics considerations when using ICTs and mobile phones in civil society, democracy, transparency, and accountability initiatives. The course is made possible by a grant from the United Nations Democracy Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-is-this-course-for&quot;&gt;Who is this course for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is designed for people at small and medium organizations, primarily non-profits and NGOs focused on democracy, civic engagement, transparency and accountability. We’ve done our best to optimize the course for low-bandwidth users. However, you will need internet connectivity in order to participate in the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-commitment&quot;&gt;What is the commitment?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will spend about 2-3 hours each week engaging with the platform and materials, with optional online clinic hours offered twice a week for people who want to ask questions in real-time. The course will run for 10 weeks, with 2 weeks for each module to accommodate busy working schedules, from 24 February-5 May 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To encourage participation and help cover some of the costs of the course, we’re charging a nominal fee of $50, payable through Paypal (or alternate means if this is not possible for you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-i-apply&quot;&gt;How do I apply?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill out our &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.frontlinesms.com/sign-up/&quot;&gt;registration form&lt;/a&gt; by 13 February. We’ll accept 35-40 participants and will let you know the status of your application by 18 February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;course-fee&quot;&gt;Course Fee&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If accepted, you will be sent a link to our PayPal account to pay your course fee of $50.00.  If you need an alternative payment arrangement, or to request a scholarship, please email &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-if-i-have-other-questions&quot;&gt;What if I have other questions?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read about the course in more depth &lt;a href=&quot;http://courses.frontlinesms.com/how-it-works/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any additional questions, send us an email at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2015 09:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/02/02/sign-up-for-our-upcoming-course</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/02/02/sign-up-for-our-upcoming-course</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Navigating A Crowded Landscape: Digital Tools in Humanitarian Response</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In November 2014, CDAC Network spoke with Laura Walker McDonald about using technology in humanitarian situations. We’ve reposted it with their kind permission. You can find the original &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdacnetwork.org/i/20141118121212-60cud/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than ever before, those responding to humanitarian emergencies have new and innovative tools out there that can help them do things they wouldn’t have been able to do before. Many of these are software tools that harness the power of the internet for speed and efficiency gains as well as manipulating and moving data in new ways, for example when capturing data from affected communities quickly for needs assessments. This trend has been documented recently in OCHA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://cdacnetwork.org/tools-and-resources/i/20140610200806-jgmnb&quot;&gt;Humanitarianism in the Network Age&lt;/a&gt; report and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cdacnetwork.org/tools-and-resources/i/20140711115559-vdtrz&quot;&gt;Red Cross World Disasters Report&lt;/a&gt; 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we ask Laura Walker McDonald from CDAC Network Member &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.simlab.org/&quot;&gt;Social Impact Lab (SIMLab)&lt;/a&gt; how humanitarian responders can navigate this crowded landscape and work out what sort of tool they need as quickly as possible, including what questions they should be asking, and when.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hi Laura, thanks for taking the time. What is the problem that humanitarian responders face when looking to find a technological solution to a problem in the field?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online software tools and platforms are in vogue right now. Every company and organisation claims to have the next best app that can do all the things a humanitarian responder could possibly need. The problem is that this isn’t really the case. When humanitarian responders are out in the field and they need to get something done quickly, like capture information from hard to reach communities, they are faced with so many options for software tools that it becomes hard to determine which is most suitable for the job. Sometimes the providers over-market their tools, other times it’s hard to find the critical information that can help the responder decide whether one tool is suitable over another. Quite frequently though, the problem is that the humanitarian responder doesn’t really know what they are looking for. This means that organisations working in technology and their associated partners need to help inform and educate practitioners, and make it easier for the humanitarian community as a whole to navigate its way through this landscape and ask the right questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what kind of challenges are we talking about? And what approach should be taken to tackle these challenges?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues are wide and varied, but it doesn’t take a technological mind to work these out. More often than not, users have certain preconceptions and assumptions about which technology they would like to use. This means they are starting with what they think the solution is, rather than the problem, which is unhelpful. They first need to think about what they want to achieve, rather than about which tools might be the best fit. Responders would be better looking at their overall objectives and asking critical high-level questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What specific questions and issues relating to technology should those working in humanitarian response pay attention to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question to ask is usually ‘What kind of information management am I doing?’ This refers to the capture, manipulation or movement of data – the essence of the task at hand. Following this primary goal, important questions exist around how this is done, before solutions are explored. Here are &lt;strong&gt;six questions&lt;/strong&gt; that may help build rounded requirements in advance of choosing a tool:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How fast do things need to be done?&lt;/strong&gt; When working in a disaster affected area, users need to think about the speed of their operation and how quickly data needs to be transferred. This overall ‘need for speed’ affects the type of connectivity that will be suitable for them. Connectivity is often the lowest common denominator. People can only go as fast as their connection will allow them to go. In the field, it is common to go for a couple of days without a connection. Does a responder need to transmit this data in real-time or can he/she wait until they hit the next Wi-Fi point to synchronise the data? Answer this and it will be easier to work out which tool is most suitable for the task. It may even be possible to combine the two, providing some data over SMS which is common, and then supplementing it with extra data over Wi-Fi/mobile data when next connected.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How much needs to be budgeted?&lt;/strong&gt; Speak to any technology manager working in humanitarian response and frequently they will explain that the amount allocated to technology, as part of projects, is nowhere near what it needs to be. When looking at tools, it is important to take into account all the different associated costs and make sure the budget can cover all aspects required to implement a tool correctly and comprehensively. This could include software, hardware, maintenance, training, airtime (for SMS messages or mobile data) and the human resources for running and managing the tool. What might seem to be a nice cost effective tool may have high implementation costs and these need to be considered during programme planning.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How suitable is it for this local area and how easy is it to use?&lt;/strong&gt; It is important to think about what kind of users will be using the tool. Does it require a software developer to be able to decipher the user interface or can anybody step into it, just like they use google or facebook? If it’s difficult to use, it will be hard to ensure uptake and will add to costs in training and roll-out in general. Costs can spiral in the long-term as specialised personnel leave and are hard to replace. On top of this, those working with the tool could be unfamiliar with English. Can the tool be localised in the language(s) of the country where it is being used? Does it support non-latin characters?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What sort of licensing model is most appropriate?&lt;/strong&gt; When starting up a technology project in a humanitarian conflict, the instinct for many managers is to immediately look towards open source software, sometimes without really understanding what that means. Open source means the code is available to modify, under certain conditions depending on the license. It doesn’t mean it’s free, although often it is. It doesn’t mean it’s more suited to social change, either. In reality going ‘open source’ brings with it its own set of disadvantages as well as advantages. Despite the promise that open source brings with it a budding developer community, for many humanitarian projects there isn’t a large community of developers ready to help expand and develop the rather specific code base, or to support a  project pro bono. User support may be hard to get, and the code may not be maintained or updated as operating systems move on. Despite not being able to freely use the code, some paid-for services can be more reliable and provide guaranteed support, customer service and long-term sustainability. On the other hand, if something is open source and the provider of the service goes out of business or stops working on it, the code base is available to use and continue working on it. Each option has unique advantages and disadvantages and these need to be weighed up when embarking on a project.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How compatible does the data need to be with other platforms and software?&lt;/strong&gt; What is more important than the open source question is whether the platform supports common data standards. This sounds complicated, but it’s not. It just means that data can be downloaded in a common format like comma separated values (CSV) or extensible markup language (XML), or as an Excel doc. If proprietary file formats are used, check there’s a good export function. Without this, it’s very difficult to move data around, share it and push it to other systems and platforms. Application programming interfaces (APIs) can also help with moving data between platforms and systems, whether or not there’s a download option, but make sure that exports and APIs allow access to ALL the data – not just a selection of the fields the provider thinks are needed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What sort of user support is needed?&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, before using a platform, try and start a conversation with the people offering it. If it is difficult to get a conversation going, it’s probably a good idea to walk away. A service provider needs to be able spend time with users and it is something that isn’t usually considered by those signing up for a tool. Imagine trying to undertake a one-off survey and all of a sudden the tool stops working. If it is difficult to get somebody on the other end of the phone to help with a query, the project is scuppered. Good practice would be to open with questions directly to service staff and actually test out their user support. It’s important and is something that differentiates professional software organisations from talented well organised amateurs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What solutions are out there to support people making a decision about what tools to use and address some of these important issues?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly the approach that has been taken is to create online directories that aim to dig out useful information about tools and provide an overview of what they do. These are usually objective and try to give the most useful information for a user. There are lots of existing directories such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://humanitarian-nomad.org/online-selection-tool/&quot;&gt;Humanitarian Nomad&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://kopernik.info/technologies&quot;&gt;Kopernik’s Technology Marketplace&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://solutionscenter.nethope.org/&quot;&gt;Nethope’s Solution Center&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdacnetwork.org/marketplace/service-directory/&quot;&gt;CDAC Network’s Service Directory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are limitations that sometimes affect these directories. Firstly, it is difficult to keep them updated with the most useful and relevant information. Good software products are updated frequently and for the directories to be useful, they at least need to provide current and up-to-date information. Some of the directories out there have fallen out of use as initial funding was not followed up and the organisation creating it was not able to provide ongoing support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some directories, companies and organisations are able to outline their tools’ capabilities themselves. This can lead to self-promotion and the overselling of features and specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of the issues with the concept of a directory, there are also issues with implementation. Some are simply badly designed or too hard to navigate. Others don’t categorise the information or make it difficult to find the relevant bits for each section. Some are no more than a list. Often less tech-savvy managers are the ones making decisions on tools and they may need to get down to brass tacks quickly. If the directory is tedious and requires dredging through, then maybe the most appropriate solution won’t rise to the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it’s actually from a tools provider, I quite liked a simple comparison chart on the Datawinners site. The specifications are honest (their own tool doesn’t always come out on top) and they checked with the providers featured when creating it to ensure the information was correct at the time of published. FrontlineSMS sent in comments and they changed it straight away. This type of transparent and objective approach is rare and appreciated as it helps to inform the community at large. On top of this the format of a comparison matrix is quick and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is SIMLab doing to help people make sense of it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SIMLab’s Frontline platform is actually going to be a separate company from the end of [2014]. That makes us ‘recovering platform providers’, with nine years of experience making technology and helping people to use it. We want to help tackle some of the problems we’ve noticed over the years, and navigating this technological expanse is one of them. Rather than enter the foray of tool directories ourselves, though, we’re taking a slightly different approach. We are planning to host a community site, joined by colleagues at think tanks, NGOs, consultants, and providers, where people can directly engage with others using these tools, and the developers who create them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many tech providers we spoke to confirmed that they wanted to offer this type of support but didn’t have the resources to do it alone. Pooling resources, we can build a central place to debate the merits and pitfalls of different tools honestly and openly, and receive support and assistance from the developers and communities using them. Our site will be cross-sector, bringing in many actors beyond humanitarian users, along with their unique insights and shared challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What role can the CDAC Network Service Directory play in making it easier for people to find the right tool?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDAC Network’s approach on the directory format with their Service Directory provides a simple entry point for organisations looking at technology tools for responders communicating with disaster affected communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curated directories such as the CDAC Network Service Directory aim to dig out the information on tools and services that users need at the beginning of their search to allow them to make an informed choice. The Directory acts as a gateway or ‘first step’ to becoming more engaged on a community site such as the one envisaged by SIMLab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 10:50:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/01/07/navigating-a-crowded-landscape</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/01/07/navigating-a-crowded-landscape</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Improving Disaster Response and Aid Delivery with ICTs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As some of you may know, we’ve had many exciting new developments over the last few months, some of which were covered in our first blog post &lt;a href=&quot;http://simlab.org/blog/2014/09/02/welcome-to-SIMLab/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. SIMLab’s focus on helping organizations to use inclusive technologies to build systems and services that are accessible, responsive, and resilient means that we’re now tool agnostic, but many of our case study resources for a while will continue to draw on our work with the Frontline product set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things we’ve been working though is our Context Assessment methodology, and how we can best articulate why and how information and communication habits and needs are critical considerations in development projects. Our newest case study, which documents ActionAid’s experience using FrontlineSMS to improve disaster-affected communities in Kenya, illustrates how crucial information flows are. It builds off blog posts on the project &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/2012/12/29/frontlinesms-at-7/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlinesms.com/2012/07/13/information-provides-real-benefits-for-drought-hit-communities-and-actionaid-alike/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and new insights about the project design and lessons learned from project documentation and ActionAid staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the project, ActionAid International Kenya and infosaid piloted an SMS-based communication and food aid delivery system. ActionAid sees information and two-way communication with communities and aid beneficiaries as essential parts of their work, and infoasaid (a DFID-funded initiative which ran from 2010-2013) was set up to support agencies to transform their approach to communicating with communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pilot took place in Isiolo, Kenya, where chronic drought, food insecurity, and violent clashes threaten to push people into crisis. Prior to the SMS system, ActionAid relied on information relayed from Field Officers as their primary communication source with food-aid recipients. Compounded by security issues, lack of infrastructure, and time constraints, communication was becoming increasingly cumbersome, erratic and infrequent. Moreover, workers and food-aid recipients lacked information on market prices, scheduled food deliveries, and other updates. To read more about how they used FrontlineSMS to tackle some of these issues, and how staff began to pick up the system to do other parts of their work, click &lt;a href=&quot;/files/frontlineSMS_actionaid_kenya_090115.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to Paul Stewart for formatting this case study as a volunteer graphic designer.  You can see his amazing work &lt;a href=&quot;http://mouthtosource.net/portfolio&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 16:17:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/01/05/improving-disaster-response-and-aid-delivery-with-icts</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2015/01/05/improving-disaster-response-and-aid-delivery-with-icts</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I meant to say at... The New York Techsalon, on our hopes and fears for 2015!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Welcome to a new blog post series, in which we post a rough account of what we said at events and on panels, based on our notes. The probability that the text makes more sense than the spoken word did—and includes fewer bad jokes—is high.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At SIMLab, we are working on some of the wicked, tech-adjacent (often human) problems that arise when you’re using technology in social change work. That means, not how to get a specific tool working, or how to get a connection or power in a remote location, although both are important; but what else happens when we use technology in a development or aid (or activism, or journalism…) project, to power balances, evidence bases, budget tracking, staff training, organizational development, and a host of other issues. We’ll be tackling a number of specific challenges in 2015, of which more later. But in general, in ‘ICT4D’ or ICT for development work, I hope that we become more collaborative; more focussed on local impact and usable learning and less on ‘scale’ (whatever that really means); and cut down on the number of parachute projects in which an external technologist arrives in a place to implement an idea untethered from the political, bureaucratic, geographic, infrastructural and cultural landscape in which they’re arriving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the project level, I hope we can learn more from each project we undertake, and make it easy to access and share what that learning. I hope we implement responsible and ethical data practices, and make them part of our safeguarding and protection requirements. SIMLab is working on how to better monitor and evaluate the contribution technology makes to projects, and will continue to look at data ethics throughout 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hope we can collectively do more of this at the sector level. &lt;a href=&quot;http://simlab.org/team#anna&quot;&gt;Anna, our SIMLab Governance Director&lt;/a&gt;, wrote me in an email recently:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Asking project-level folks to take on the burden of proving sector-wide impact limits project-level learning (depletes resources) and overwhelms sector-wide learning with a lot of noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d agree, and I’d also recommend Dave Algoso’s excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://algoso.org/2014/12/16/case-studies-as-a-tool-for-sector-learning/&quot;&gt;recent post on case studies&lt;/a&gt;, which is very relevant here. Exhorting people to learn and share learning doesn’t solve the absorption problem. We probably need a better sectoral community of practice, and a way (a resource? A group of people?) to turn many shared evaluation reports (itself a dream) into usable, accessible knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, looking at the technology itself; I hope that we’ll not build only for a smartphone future, ignoring the power and access problems that keep people using feature phones, and get real about &lt;a href=&quot;https://gsmaintelligence.com/analysis/2014/05/measuring-mobile-penetration/430/&quot;&gt;what mobile industry statistics really mean&lt;/a&gt;. Many, many people still get their information through more inclusive technologies, like feature phones, radio, and human networks, and those channels need to be better understood and utilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think it’s time to look carefully at what a decade or more of funding and working on innovation in this area has wrought, and why. We need to examine what we think ‘innovation’ is—sometimes it might not be the technology that needs to change, but the implementation methodology. How many times does a practitioner need the resources to do their development work better, but have to cloak it in a shiny new ICT wrapping to get it funded? Perhaps the field should fund the field - why not have a revolving fund administered by practitioners, for practitioners, topped up by subscriptions and grants, with the quid pro quo being that accessible learning I mentioned earlier?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I have a sense of optimism about ICT4D, and of forward progress, but I think the balance is at times more in favour of expensive big ideas without substantive underpinnings, than in the slow, careful work of supporting and learning from locally-implemented good ideas that use appropriate, sustainable tools. My hope for 2015 is that we continue to make steps in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 10:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2014/12/31/what-i-meant-to-say-at-ny-techsalon</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2014/12/31/what-i-meant-to-say-at-ny-techsalon</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SIMLab’s Mobile Technology Trainings for NGOs Launches as an Online Course</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In September 2014, supported by funding from the United Nations Democracy Education Fund (UNDEF)  the &lt;a href=&quot;http://simlab.org/governance/&quot;&gt;Governance Project&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://simlab.org/&quot;&gt;Social Impact Lab&lt;/a&gt; launched a new web platform for training and supporting civil society organizations on how to use inclusive technology in their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural course supported 21 participants from 17 organizations across eight countries (mostly from across Africa and Asia) to plan for and use mobile technologies in their democracy, transparency, and accountability related work. UNDEF are supporting us to run several more courses like this throughout 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/simlabrefresh/images/post_images/undef_ss.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fluid post image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Materials presented throughout the course drew heavily on institutional knowledge accumulated from thousands of technical support questions answered on the FrontlineSMS and FrontlineCloud platforms as well as lessons learned in conducting context and mobile infrastructure assessments, data integrity analyses, navigating non-governmental politics, and supporting SMS project planning in dozens of countries and sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since NGOs and their staff are often stretched for both time and resources, we attempted design the course in a way that would adapt easily to busy schedules, tight budgets, and inconsistent connectivity levels. The flexible presentation of course materials seemed helpful for balancing busy schedules, though we underestimated difficulties in accommodating different connectivity levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussions, readings, and hangouts incorporated program design and planning cycle considerations in low cost, low bandwidth environments, including how the choice of communications platform can be inclusive or exclusive, and how to identify and mitigate risk. The final course module focused on monitoring and evaluation techniques for mobile-centered or mobile-enabled projects using SMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have a lot of work to do and are grateful for the feedback that beta participants gave us on how to better address connectivity issues, accommodate time constraints, and consider existing workstreams. A key challenge and a key piece of learning is that it’s tough to teach an online course, using audio and video resources, on technology for low-bandwidth environments. For the future we’re challenging ourselves to come up with a way to provide interactive learning without demanding too much of our participants’ internet connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in early 2015, we’ll open registration for additional online trainings, demos, and platform-specific learning related to mobile- and inclusive-technologies.  In the meantime, we are working to integrate lessons learned from this ‘beta’ course into future iterations, and exploring subject matter for future courses. For more information or to find out about the next course announcement, email us at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#109;&amp;#108;&amp;#097;&amp;#098;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/simlabrefresh/images/post_images/undef_logo.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fluid half post image&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 10:12:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2014/12/11/simlabs-mobile-technology-training</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2014/12/11/simlabs-mobile-technology-training</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog,</category>
        
        <category>announcements</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Credit and Fraud: How One M-PESA User Weighs Risk on Kenya&#39;s Largest Mobile Money Platform</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently in Kisumu, a semi-rural area on the coast of Lake Victoria in Western Kenya. I was there for ten days; training organizations on our mobile payments software, collecting indicators to monitor our DFID project and connecting with organizations to work with in the future. One of the places I spent the most time over the week was Support for Tropical Initiatives in Poverty Alleviation (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stipakenya.org/&quot;&gt;STIPA&lt;/a&gt;), which is an amazing organization with projects in microfinance, health insurance, and economic opportunity programs. My time at STIPA was made very worthwhile by the dedicated, knowledgeable and passionate staff. We’ll be working closely with STIPA as they merge two of their major programs, Community Based Health Financing and Village Savings and Loaning to begin using mobile payments. They’re two very impactful projects with unique challenges and potential gains, more of which we’ll be highlighting in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/simlabrefresh/images/post_images/peter.jpg&quot; class=&quot;small right blogfloated image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we won’t focus on STIPA, but rather on STIPA’s Social Marketing Officer, Peter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to spend an afternoon with Peter when, because of a torrential storm and subsequent power outage, we were left unable to work on the desktop computers. I took it as an opportunity to learn more about the culture of M-PESA to share with those who have little, or no experience with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter is a young Kenyan who was recently living in Nairobi but has now relocated to Kisumu to work for STIPA. Peter’s been using M-PESA now for over five years and considers it a valuable tool, but doesn’t think about it that often, as it’s just a part of his daily (or monthly) life. When I spoke with Peter it was mid October and Peter currently had 12,000-15,000ksh (roughly $130-$165USD) on his M-PESA mWallet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;m-pesa-part-of-daily-life&quot;&gt;M-PESA: part of daily life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interested to find out how Peter uses M-PESA in a typical month and question why he’s not using it in other ways. Peter described a typical monthly interaction for me. 
He’s paid his monthly salary through a direct deposit into his bank account, and withdraws approximately 30,000ksh (roughly $330USD) and deposits that amount onto his M-PESA account by visiting a large M-PESA agent at a nearby shopping centre. Peter shows the agent his government issued ID, confirms his mobile number, signs the register and hands over the cash. He then receives an SMS from M-PESA confirming his cash was deposited onto his mobile account. The entire transaction takes approximately 1 minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter makes this deposit onto his M-PESA account so that he can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pay for bills (electricity, water, internet) by sending directly through M-PESA to his accounts using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.safaricom.co.ke/personal/m-pesa/m-pesa-services-tariffs/paybill/pay-bill&quot;&gt;PayBill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Withdraw from M-PESA at a later time to buy food and house supplies from the grocery store.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, he does this because it’s easier, and cheaper for him to withdraw using M-PESA than it is to use his own bank card for numerous transactions, plus its impossible to pay electricity/water/internet bills using his bank card. Nonetheless, he does not pay for groceries at the supermarket using mobile money, even though it’s possible at most large grocery stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked why he doesn’t keep his entire monthly salary on the M-PESA mWallet, Peter had two very quick answers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s too easy to spend money on M-PESA, if he kept it all on his M-PESA mWallet it may be spent very easily and quickly decrease his savings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s impossible to build up credit through M-PESA. Peter said he’s looking at applying for a loan soon, for which he will need a credit history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;m-pesa-and-credit&quot;&gt;M-PESA and credit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, (though it’s changing) loans are only available if money is kept in an accredited bank account. This is one of the major incentives of joining a Sacco (Savings and Credit Cooperative) since you’re able to rely on other members of the group for loans which exceed your personal worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access to credit—even microloans of just $10-$50 USD—are hard to come by for the unbanked. It’s one of the major issues plaguing the poor who aren’t able to invest beyond their personal available capital. This difficulty, a kind of financial glass ceiling, is being addressed in unique and innovative ways by various actors. Two such companies looking to change how last mile, low-income populations access credit using mobile are &lt;a href=&quot;http://inventure.com&quot;&gt;Inventure&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.firstaccessmarket.com&quot;&gt;First Access&lt;/a&gt;. Inventure is able to predict creditworthiness by helping low-income people with tracking their finances by tracking financial information on an Android application. When applying for a loan, a user can point to their recent savings and expense history as evidence of creditworthiness. After a quick multiple choice questionnaire, the loan can be approved instantly. First Access, on the other hand combines financial and recent mobile data usage, such as the amount of the person’s most recent top up, number of days with no mobile traffic, and other data as proxy indicators to predict creditworthiness through an algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;everybodys-worried-about-phantom-fraud&quot;&gt;Everybody’s worried about phantom fraud&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked what could be improved about M-PESA, Peter quickly responded that issues to deal with fraud need to be addressed - although he personally has not ever experienced fraud while using the mobile money service. This immediate, almost unconscious answer unaccompanied by a heart-wrenching story, caught my interest. Is the real threat of fraud as high as it’s portrayed? How often does it actually occur?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my conversation with Peter, I spoke with five other employees, none of whom had ever personally experienced fraud with M-PESA, but all of whom insisted it was a concern. A quick internet search revealed that, according to Bob Collymore, CEO of M-PESA’s parent company Safaricom, M-PESA fraud occurrence for customers is around 0.002 percent, and for merchants it is 0.007. For comparison, the average credit cards fraud rate is 0.05 percent (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.the-star.co.ke/news/article-117102/m-pesa-fraud-losses-less-1-safaricom&quot;&gt;The Star&lt;/a&gt;). That means that out of every 1,000 people, only 2 will experience fraud over M-PESA as opposed to 50 with a credit card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I asked a different group of young people about their concerns with credit cards, would the first concern listed have been fraud? It seems unlikely—but it does seem that unfounded concerns are deeply associated with M-PESA, something that clearly needs to be addressed if we want to see stronger growth in take-up and usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-are-we-overestimating-the-rural-float-challenge&quot;&gt;But are we overestimating the ‘rural float’ challenge?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last interesting piece of information Peter volunteered, was that in the last 3 months, he can’t remember ever having a problem withdrawing or depositing cash at an agent. Mobile float issues arise when the agent either does not have enough cash to hand out, in exchange for the M-PESA sent, or when someone is trying to deposit cash at an agent and the agent does not have enough on their mWallet to send to the depositor in exchange for the cash. The ‘rural float’ problem has often been cited as the reason mobile money fails to gain traction in rural areas. However, Kisumu is a large city and Peter tends to visit only large agents located at the supermarket, so it may just be an area where the mobile money ecosystem is functioning in equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-does-this-all-mean&quot;&gt;So what does this all mean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, it means mobile money is not where it needs to be to support the transition to a more cashless society - even in Kenya, arguably the world’s most developed mobile economy. More financial products need to be available through mobile money for users to access loans, better savings mechanisms need to be in place to encourage saving and prevent irresponsible spending, and there needs to be more focus on user education around the true incidence of fraud and how to prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest barrier to using alternatives to cash, whether in Kisumu, across Kenya or globally, is the need for behavior change—awareness of alternatives and the courage to test them. But this is also at the core of its potential—in Kenya, as in much of the developing world, youth represent the majority of the population, and as this tech-savvy market segment grow into their purchasing power and begin to try out new mobile money products, we predict an explosion of mobile financial products to serve them. Some of this will be possible through products targeting young people specifically. Others will offer benefits such as interest-bearing mobile savings accounts, the ability to develop a credit history, loyalty vouchers, and links with social media. Critically, they will need to be fast, efficient and easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition in the market will be beneficial—the more businesses there are thinking about how to attract new customers and grow traffic, the better. This will spur more and better targeted ideas, and allow for rapid prototyping of new and edgy product ideas. Interoperability is also at the core of this - the easier we can make it for people to innovate on top of service infrastructure like M-PESA, the faster uptake and throughput will grow. APIs will be good news for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We aren’t there yet, and have some significant hurdles to cross, but understanding how mobile money is being used by the average person gives us an insight into where effort needs to be focused in order to increase usage, desirability and trust.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2014 10:12:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2014/12/02/credit-and-fraud</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2014/12/02/credit-and-fraud</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>M&amp;E of ICTs4D: Project Level Learning in an Evolving Sector</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;ICT4D and M4D as fields are both exciting and clumsy, still in their infancy and most consistent in how quickly they are changing. The&lt;a href=&quot;http://mandetech.org/agenda-nyc/&quot;&gt; M&amp;amp;E Tech Deep Dive in New York&lt;/a&gt; in early October 2014 mustered up familiar conversations around monitoring and evaluation, as well as around ICT4D. Beyond the use of ICTs &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; M&amp;amp;E, finding common ground on the evaluation &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; ICTs was challenging. There is wide consensus that technology is not a silver bullet, and further, that it simply can’t be separated from the context in which it operates or is applied. How then, can we think about monitoring and evaluating the role of a particular ICT or digital platform in the context of a larger initiative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deep Dive affirmed that one organization’s innovation is another organization’s absence of evidence.  In other words, participants from different sectors and backgrounds had similar questions yet seemed to be speaking different languages. Two participants summed up the range of sentiments well.  The first person recounted that ‘off-the-shelf’ platforms had been mentioned several times throughout the conference, yet no one there could point to an experience of using one without the need for extended assistance, additional tools, or diverting additional resources from other programs (usually in short supply). Another attendee relayed that in the early 1990s, companies and non-profits alike needed to strategize on how the Internet could be used in their daily work. In 2014, the Internet is indistinguishable from operations in many cities around the world: from email to search engines, to travel arrangements and daily news and the list continues. The first commenter conveyed that while ICTs (including mobile) are put forward to simplify and transform, they require &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of work, and can be far more complex and costly (both in ethical and material terms) than the proposed benefits they offer. We need evaluation! The second commenter highlighted that the global shift toward digital is increasingly inevitable (in some form or another) and that investing significant organizational resources to prove that ICTs are useful may seem like a futile exercise (with possibly high costs) to affirm the obvious. Is evaluation really worthwhile?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gap between immediate utility and longer-term impact, for better or&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; worse, of ICTs can be attributed to any number of factors, including politics or competing priorities, neither of of which is unique to ICTs. Though it is clear that this gap reflects another rift, one between how the use of ICTs is conceived for specific projects and programs (often aligned with proposals and funding timelines) and the realities of a sector for which the infrastructure is still being laid, with many different forces and factors shaping accessibility, support, service areas, civil and political rights, and information regulation among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appropriate uses of technology are found somewhere in between trial-and-error and a growing, albeit very incomplete, repository of experiences and evidence base. There is a clear bias in the stories and experiences that are circulated (and thus those that get noticed and counted), toward organizations that are well resourced enough to synthesize and publish their findings, toward individuals that leverage social media, and toward those who attend global conferences. These groups’ stories and experiences often drive, and even become, the conversation. Those without the resources for visibility, though with important insights and perspectives on the same applications, are often left out of the conversation entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot we don’t know about ICT4D. There are many voices that remain peripheral, or altogether invisible, in the conversation. What we do know is that there are big differences in thinking about ICTs at the project level and thinking about them more widely as part of an evolving sector. We also know that all programs (whether in the public, multilateral or non-governmental sectors) involve power dynamics and decision-making challenges during organizational planning and program execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we continue listening to, learning about, and engaging with various approaches to M&amp;amp;E of ICT for development, here’s a summary of what we discussed in one session at M&amp;amp;E Tech NYC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;separate-monitoring-of-ict-toolsplatforms-into-three-phases&quot;&gt;Separate monitoring of ICT tools/platforms into three phases:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying a tool or platform in ‘development’ involves different phases and approaches. In one discussion at M&amp;amp;E Tech NYC, we distinguished between three phases of ICT application and evaluation, with the intention of better assessment and learning for continuous improvement. These three phases were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rollout.&lt;/em&gt; The rollout phase is the initial window when a tool or platform is first adopted or applied, whether that tool or platform is completely new, a new component of an existing system, or an effort to integrate two or more existing systems or platforms. It is a window when active observation and active adjustments are prioritized. Rollout is contained, almost always messy, and things often go wrong. (In other words, there is no ‘formula’.) In technology, it is accepted practice to ‘fail fast’ - a counterintuitive approach for development practitioners, who think about failure in terms of trade-offs whose cost is borne largely by the most vulnerable. In the rollout of new technologies, a thing breaking or dropping out mid-action is not only normal, but expected. This recognition can alleviate some of the pressure on how evaluations count what is ‘good’ and what ‘needs to improve’. While it doesn’t minimize the importance of understanding the cost (and who bears it), evaluation of a rollout might focus more on organizational learning than longer-term ‘impact’ of activities. Every phase should calculate, minimize, and mitigate risks to people involved or affected.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Implementation.&lt;/em&gt; Implementation takes place after rollout, when lessons have been learned and a tool or product has been adapted. Evaluating implementation normally focuses on how people, context, decisions, and outcomes interact with the technology. How to do this, unsurprisingly, varies and is often a source of great debate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Long-term use, adoption, and sustainability.&lt;/em&gt; Sustainability of ICTs is similar to other programs or projects. Resources, training, buy-in, and legitimacy issues are some of many factors that affect the long-term use and sustainability of ICTs. System requirements, upgrades, and interoperability considerations add new sustainability questions to consider. (These technical considerations are another blog post, or series, entirely.) Regardless, evaluating sustainability and rollout, without distinguishing between the two phases may compress different kinds of activities into an unhelpful average that undermines, rather than enhances, learning and shared benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evaluative-questions&quot;&gt;Evaluative questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the different phases mentioned above, it may be useful to answer three kinds of questions when evaluating the role of technology tools and platforms in development programming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the role of technology in organizational processes and is there ease of adoption among those using it?&lt;/em&gt; Here we can try to identify how and where technologies and platforms change (or are intended to change) organizational processes as well as how receptive team members are to using them. If multiple technologies and platforms are used at different points in an organizational process (say, prioritizing service delivery according to need and geography), trying to isolate the impact of just one may not be the goal as much as identifying points for greater compatibility between and among systems and tools used.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the role of tech in decision-making and program outcomes?&lt;/em&gt; Here we may want to ask how the data collected (whether through SMS, maps, sensors, etc.) change the way decisions are made, transform working or reporting relationships (whether due to shifts in cost, power dynamics or anything else) or how the ICT’s role has shifted from rollout to implementation to long-term adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What level and type of tech support is provided or needed?&lt;/em&gt; ICT4D or M4D ‘solutions’ are not often actually simple “solutions” to problems. Most tools and platforms require ongoing support for the people using them, for data analysis, and for integrating a tool’s functions with other tools or systems being used for similar purposes. Keeping an eye on how much support and learning is needed (and supplied) as part of ICT evaluations can help to assess how sustainable, user friendly and cost-effective the technology tool or platform is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are many open questions about how to understand and separate the data integrity, security, surveillance and consent considerations of any ICT application, program or platform. While guides, indices, and regulatory approaches are emerging to help navigate these considerations, they were explored in greater detail during several other sessions at the NYC Deep Dive. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2014 14:18:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/simlabrefresh/blog/2014/11/26/m-and-e-of-icts4d-project-level-learning-in-an-evolving-sector</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/simlabrefresh/blog/2014/11/26/m-and-e-of-icts4d-project-level-learning-in-an-evolving-sector</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
